Let's face it:
لنقوم بمواجهة الأمر..
Driving is dangerous.
قيادة السيارات خطرة
It's one of the things that we don't like to think about,
هي أحدى الأمور التي لا نريد أن نفكر بها
but the fact that religious icons and good luck charms
لكن حقيقة أن الأيقونات الدينية و تعويذات الحظ السعيد
show up on dashboards around the world
تظهر على لوحات القيادة في السيارات حول العالم
betrays the fact that we know this to be true.
تضلل الحقيقة بأننا نعلم أن هذا يمكن أن يكون حقيقي
Car accidents are the leading cause of death
حوادث السيارة هي السبب المؤدي الى الموت
in people ages 16 to 19 in the United States --
لدى أشخاص من عمر 16 الى 19 في الولايات المتحدة
leading cause of death --
السبب المودي الى الموت
and 75 percent of these accidents have nothing to do
و 75 بالمئة من هذه الحوادث غير متعلقة
with drugs or alcohol.
بالمخدرات أو الكحول
So what happens?
اذا ما ذا يحدث؟
No one can say for sure, but I remember my first accident.
لا أحد يستطيع القول بالتأكيد, لكنني أتذكر أول حادث حصل لي
I was a young driver out on the highway,
كنت سائقة شابة على الطريق السريع
and the car in front of me, I saw the brake lights go on.
رأيت ضوء المكابح على السيارة التي كانت أمامي
I'm like, "Okay, all right, this guy is slowing down,
كأنني, حسنا", حسنا", هذا الشخص يبطء السرعة
I'll slow down too."
سأبطئ السرعة أيضا"
I step on the brake.
دست على المكابح
But no, this guy isn't slowing down.
لكن لا, هذا الشخص لا يبطئ
This guy is stopping, dead stop, dead stop on the highway.
انه يتوقف, وقوف كامل, وقوف كامل على الطريق السريع
It was just going 65 -- to zero?
كانت السرعة تنتقل من 65-- الى صفر
I slammed on the brakes.
دست على المكابح بقوة
I felt the ABS kick in, and the car is still going,
شعرت بأن المكابح ذات النظام المضاد للاقفال تصدر صوت, و السيارة ما تزال تسير
and it's not going to stop, and I know it's not going to stop,
و أن السيارة لن تتوقف, و أنا أعلم بأنها لن تتوقف
and the air bag deploys, the car is totaled,
و انتفخ كيس الهواء, و قد أصيبت السيارة
and fortunately, no one was hurt.
و لحسن الحظ لم يصاب أحد
But I had no idea that car was stopping,
لكنني لم أعرف ما سبب توقف تلك السيارة
and I think we can do a lot better than that.
و أعتقد أنه باستطاعتنا أن نقوم بعمل أفضل من ذلك
I think we can transform the driving experience
أعتقد بأننا نستطيع أن ننقل تجارب القيادة
by letting our cars talk to each other.
من خلال اعطاء الفرصة لسياراتنا لتتحدث لبعضها
I just want you to think a little bit
أريدكم أن تفكروا و لو لقليلا"
about what the experience of driving is like now.
حول ماهية خبرة قيادة السيارات الآن
Get into your car. Close the door. You're in a glass bubble.
اصعد إلى السيارة, أغلق الباب, أنت الآن في فقاعة زجاجية
You can't really directly sense the world around you.
لا يمكنك حقا" أن تشعر بالعالم المحيط حولك
You're in this extended body.
انت في هذا الجسم الممتد
You're tasked with navigating it down
مهمتك هي التنقل عليه
partially-seen roadways,
الطرقات المرئية جزئيا"
in and amongst other metal giants, at super-human speeds.
ما بين العمالقة المعدنية, بسرعات جنونية
Okay? And all you have to guide you are your two eyes.
حسنا" و كل ما تملكه ليقودك هو عيناك
Okay, so that's all you have,
حسنا", هذا كل ما تملك
eyes that weren't really designed for this task,
عيون هي بالأصل غير مصممة لهذا الغرض
but then people ask you to do things like,
لكن فيما بعد يسألك الناس لفعل شي مثل,
you want to make a lane change,
أن تغير الممر
what's the first thing they ask you do?
ما هو أول شيء يطلبوه منك لتفعل؟
Take your eyes off the road. That's right.
أن تزيح عيناك عن الطريق أمامك, هذا صحيح
Stop looking where you're going, turn,
أن تتوقف من النظر أين ذاهب, تدير نفسك
check your blind spot,
لتتفقد البقعة العمياء جانبك
and drive down the road without looking where you're going.
و أن تقود في الطريق بدون أن تنظر أين تسير
You and everyone else. This is the safe way to drive.
أنتم و كل شخص. هذه الطريقة الآمنة للقيادة...
Why do we do this? Because we have to,
لماذا نفعل ذلك؟ لأنه يجب علينا فعله..
we have to make a choice, do I look here or do I look here?
يجب علينا أن نختار, هل أنظر هنا أو أنظر هناك؟
What's more important?
ما هو الأكثر أهمية؟
And usually we do a fantastic job
و في الواقع نحن نقوم بعمل رائع
picking and choosing what we attend to on the road.
انتقاء و اختيار اين نكون على الطريق
But occasionally we miss something.
لكن بعض الأحيان نفتقد شيئا"
Occasionally we sense something wrong or too late.
أحيانا نشعر بشيئ خاطئ أو متأخر
In countless accidents, the driver says,
في حوادث لا تعد, يقول السائق,
"I didn't see it coming."
"لم أره قادم"
And I believe that. I believe that.
و أنا أصدق ذلك, أصدق ذلك
We can only watch so much.
بامكاننا ان نراقب الكثير
But the technology exists now that can help us improve that.
لكن التقنية موجودة الآن لمساعدتنا أن نحسن ذلك
In the future, with cars exchanging data with each other,
في المستقبل, بوجود سيارات تتبادل المعلومات فيما بينها
we will be able to see not just three cars ahead
سوف يكون بامكاننا أن نرى, ليس فقط ثلاثة سيارات أمامنا فحسب
and three cars behind, to the right and left,
و ثلاثة سيارات خلفنا, الى اليمين و اليسار
all at the same time, bird's eye view,
كل الجهات في نفس الوقت, كالنظر بعين الطائر
we will actually be able to see into those cars.
سوف يكون بمقدورنا رؤية داخل تلك السيارات
We will be able to see the velocity of the car in front of us,
سوف نتمكن من ملاحظة سرعة السيارة التي أمامنا
to see how fast that guy's going or stopping.
لنعرف ما هي السرعة التي يقود بها هذا الشخص أو التي يتوقف بها
If that guy's going down to zero, I'll know.
اذا كان هذا الشخص سيتوقف بشكل كامل, سوف أعرف ذلك
And with computation and algorithms and predictive models,
مع علم الحاسوب و الخوارزميات و النماذج التنبؤية
we will be able to see the future.
سوف نتمكن من رؤية المستقبل
You may think that's impossible.
يمكن أن تجد ذلك مستحيلا"
How can you predict the future? That's really hard.
كيف بامكانك أن تتنبأ بالمستقبل؟ هذا فعلا صعب
Actually, no. With cars, it's not impossible.
بالواقع, لا, ليس بمستحيل تطبيقه على السيارات
Cars are three-dimensional objects
السيارات هي مجسمات ثلاثية الأبعاد
that have a fixed position and velocity.
حيث لديها موقع و سرعة تابتين
They travel down roads.
يسافرون على الطرقات
Often they travel on pre-published routes.
مرارا" يسافرون على طرقات غير جاهزة
It's really not that hard to make reasonable predictions
ليس من الصعب حقا" القيام بتنبؤات معقولة
about where a car's going to be in the near future.
حول الموضع الذي ستكون به السيارة في المستقبل القريب
Even if, when you're in your car
حتى عندما تكون في سيارتك
and some motorcyclist comes -- bshoom! --
و تصادفك دراجة نارية --بشووم!
85 miles an hour down, lane-splitting --
تسير بسرعة 85 ميل بالساعة و تشاطرك الممر--
I know you've had this experience --
أعرف بأنكم مررتم بظرف كهذا--
that guy didn't "just come out of nowhere."
لم يأتي هذا الشخص " من المجهول"
That guy's been on the road probably for the last half hour.
ربما هذا الشخص كان متواجد على الطريق لمدة النصف ساعة الماضية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Right? I mean, somebody's seen him.
صحيح؟ أقصد, أن شخص ما قد رآه
Ten, 20, 30 miles back, someone's seen that guy,
10, 20, 30 ميل الى الوراء, أحدهم قد رأى هذا الشخص
and as soon as one car sees that guy
و بمجرد ما تشاهد سيارة هذا الشخص
and puts him on the map, he's on the map --
و تضعه هلى الخريطة, هو على الخريطة--
position, velocity,
موضع, و سرعة,
good estimate he'll continue going 85 miles an hour.
تقدير جيد أنه سيستمر السير بسرعة 85 ميل بالساعة
You'll know, because your car will know, because
سوف تعرف, لأن سيارتك سوف تعرف, لأن
that other car will have whispered something in his ear,
السيارة الأخرى ستكون قد همست في اذنه بشيء
like, "By the way, five minutes,
مثل, "بالمناسبة, خمس دقائق,
motorcyclist, watch out."
سائق دراجة نارية, ترقب"
You can make reasonable predictions about how cars behave.
بامكانك أن تقوم بتنبؤ مقبول حول سلوك السيارات
I mean, they're Newtonian objects.
أقصد, هي أجسام نيوتونية
That's very nice about them.
و هذا جميل جدا عنهم
So how do we get there?
اذا" كيف بامكاننا التوصل لذلك
We can start with something as simple
نستطيع أن نبدأ بشي بسيط
as sharing our position data between cars,
بمشاركة معلومات مواقعنا بين السيارات
just sharing GPS.
فقط مشاركة "نظام تحديد المواقع العالمي" GPS
If I have a GPS and a camera in my car,
اذا كان لدي نظام تحديد المواقع العالمي و كاميرا بسيارتي
I have a pretty precise idea of where I am
سوف يكون لدي فكرة عن المكان الذي أنا فيه
and how fast I'm going.
و السرعة التي أقود بها
With computer vision, I can estimate where
و برؤية الحاسوب, أستطيع أن أقيّم أين
the cars around me are, sort of, and where they're going.
تتوضع السيارات حولي, نوعا" ما, و أين هي متوجهة
And same with the other cars.
و نفس الشيء بالنسبة للسيارات الأخرى
They can have a precise idea of where they are,
سوف يكون لديهم فكرة دقيقة عن موضعهم
and sort of a vague idea of where the other cars are.
و فكرة مبهمة نوعا" ما حول مكان السيارات الأخرى
What happens if two cars share that data,
ماذا يحصل اذا تشاركت سيارتان هذه المعلومات
if they talk to each other?
اذا تحدثو فيما بينهم؟
I can tell you exactly what happens.
سوف أقول لكم بالضبط ماذا يحصل
Both models improve.
كلا النموذجين يتحسنا
Everybody wins.
الجميع يفوز
Professor Bob Wang and his team
البروفيسور بوب و فريقه
have done computer simulations of what happens
قد أجرو عمليات محاكاة على الحاسوب لما يجري
when fuzzy estimates combine, even in light traffic,
عند الجمع بين تقديرات غامضة, حتى في حركة السير الخفيفة
when cars just share GPS data,
عندما تقوم السيارات بمشاركة معلومات ال GPS فقط
and we've moved this research out of the computer simulation
لقد نقلنا هذا البحث من محاكاة الكومبيوتر
and into robot test beds that have the actual sensors
الى أجسام آلية للاختبار, حيث لديها اجهزة استشعار حقيقية
that are in cars now on these robots:
التي تتواجد في السيارات الآن على هذه الروبوتات
stereo cameras, GPS,
كاميرات ستيريو, GPS,
and the two-dimensional laser range finders
و ليزر ثنائي الأبعاد لاستكشاف النطاق
that are common in backup systems.
هذا أمر شائع في أنظمة النسخ الاحتياطي
We also attach a discrete short-range communication radio,
و وصلنا أيضا" راديو مميز قصير المدى للتواصل
and the robots talk to each other.
و الروبوتات تتواصل فيما بينها
When these robots come at each other,
عندما تقترب فيما بينها
they track each other's position precisely,
يقومون بتعقب مواقع كل واحد منهم بشكل دقيق
and they can avoid each other.
و يمكنهم تجنب بعضهم البعض
We're now adding more and more robots into the mix,
نقوم باضافة العديد و العديد من الروبوتات الى المجموعة
and we encountered some problems.
و نقوم بخلق بعض العقبات
One of the problems, when you get too much chatter,
احدى هذه العقبات أنه عندما يكون لديك الكثير من الثرثرة
it's hard to process all the packets, so you have to prioritize,
يكون من الصعب تنسيق عمليات الرزم, فيتوجب عليك أختيار الأولوية
and that's where the predictive model helps you.
و هنا يقوم النموذج التنبؤي بمساعدتك
If your robot cars are all tracking the predicted trajectories,
اذا قامت سياراتك الآلية بتعقب المسارات المتوقعة
you don't pay as much attention to those packets.
لن تقوم بالاهتمام كثيرا" لهذه الرزم
You prioritize the one guy
سوفت تعطي الأولوية لذلك الشخص
who seems to be going a little off course.
الذي يبدو أنه يسير قليلا" خارج المسار
That guy could be a problem.
ربما يكون هذا الشخص هو المشكلة
And you can predict the new trajectory.
ستستطيع أن تتنبأ بالمسار الجديد
So you don't only know that he's going off course, you know how.
حيث أنك لا تعرف فحسب أنه يسير خارج المسار, تعرف كيف
And you know which drivers you need to alert to get out of the way.
و تعرف اي سائقين تحتاج لأن تنبههم ليبعدو من الطريق
And we wanted to do -- how can we best alert everyone?
و أردنا أن نقوم-- كيف بامكاننا أن ننبه الجميع؟
How can these cars whisper, "You need to get out of the way?"
كيف تستطيع هذه السيارات أن تهمس, عليك أن تبتعد من الطريق؟
Well, it depends on two things:
حسنا", يتوقف هذا على شيئين:
one, the ability of the car,
الأول, قدرة السيارة
and second the ability of the driver.
و الثاني هو قدرة السائق
If one guy has a really great car,
اذا كان شخص ما يملك سيارة ممتازة
but they're on their phone or, you know, doing something,
لكنه يستعمل التليفون أو, تعرفون, يقوم بعمل ما,
they're not probably in the best position
انه على الأغلب ليس في الموضع المناسب
to react in an emergency.
للتصرف في الحالات الطارئة
So we started a separate line of research
لذلك, بدأنا بالقيام بخط بحث منفصل
doing driver state modeling.
القيام بنمذجة حالة السائق
And now, using a series of three cameras,
و استخدام سلسلة من ثلاث كاميرات الآن
we can detect if a driver is looking forward,
يمكننا معرفة اذا كان السائق ينظر الى الأمام
looking away, looking down, on the phone,
ينظر بعيدا", ينظر الى الأسفل, على الهاتف,
or having a cup of coffee.
أو لديه كأس من القهوة
We can predict the accident
يمكننا أن نتنبأ بالحادث
and we can predict who, which cars,
و يمكننا أن نتنبأ من, أي سيارات
are in the best position to move out of the way
هي في أفضل المواقع للابتعاد من الطريق
to calculate the safest route for everyone.
للقيام بمعرفة الطريق الآمن للجميع
Fundamentally, these technologies exist today.
أساسا", هذه التكنولوجيات متواجدة اليوم
I think the biggest problem that we face
أعتقد أن من أكبر العقبات التي نواجهها
is our own willingness to share our data.
هي رغبتنا بمشاركة معلوماتنا
I think it's a very disconcerting notion,
أعتقد بأنها فكرة مقلقة للغاية
this idea that our cars will be watching us,
فكرة أن السيارات الأخرى سوف تقوم بمراقبتنا
talking about us to other cars,
تقوم بالتحدث عنا الى السيارات الأخرى
that we'll be going down the road in a sea of gossip.
و أنه سوف نسير في الطريق ضمن بحر من الأقاويل
But I believe it can be done in a way that protects our privacy,
لكنني أعتقد بأنه يمكن القيام بذلك بطريقة تحمي فيها خصوصيتنا
just like right now, when I look at your car from the outside,
بالضبط مثل الوقت الحالي, عندما أنظر الى سيارتك من الخارج
I don't really know about you.
لا أعرف حقا" أي شيء عنك
If I look at your license plate number,
أو عندما أنظر الى رقم لوحة الرخصة
I don't really know who you are.
لا أعرف حقا" من تكون
I believe our cars can talk about us behind our backs.
أعتقد بأن سياراتنا تتحدث عنا من ورائنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I think it's going to be a great thing.
أظن بأن ذلك سيكون شيء رائع
I want you to consider for a moment
أريد منكم أن تأخذو بعين الاعتبار للحظة
if you really don't want the distracted teenager behind you
اذا كنتم حقا" لا تريدون تشتيت انتباه مراهق يقود خلفكم
to know that you're braking,
لمعرفة أنكم تستعملون المكابح
that you're coming to a dead stop.
و أنكم تقومون بتوقف كامل
By sharing our data willingly,
من خلال مشاركة معلوماتنا بارادتنا
we can do what's best for everyone.
نستطيع القيام ما هو أفضل للجميع
So let your car gossip about you.
لذلك دع سيارتك تثرثر عنك
It's going to make the roads a lot safer.
سوف تقوم بجعل الطريق أكثر أمانا"
Thank you.
شكرا" لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)